

# René L Warren

warrenlr@gmail.com 778.386.4192 rer

renewarren.ca

# About me

I am a researcher with over 20 years experience in biotechnology, genomics and informatics

I have played a central role in managing the bioinformatics of large international collaborations to decrypt the genomes of *Rhodococus*, *Cryptococcus*, Bullfrog and Spruce

I developed the first program for genome assembly with then emerging short DNA sequences and pioneered the development of technologies that enabled the discovery of *Fusobacterium* in colon cancer, one of *Time Magazine*'s top ten medical breakthrough of 2011

I currently lead the BC Genome Sciences Centre's bioinformatics technology lab In that role, I have conceptualized/led the development of genome scaffolders for long read data

I am eager to take on additional challenges and leadership

# PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

Feb 2017 – **Group Leader** 

Present

BC Cancer Agency - Genome Sciences Centre, Vancouver BC

- Provide project leadership, expertise, guidance
- · Plan / coordinate group activities
- Supervise / mentor biologists and programmers
- Conceptualize development of bioinformatics technologies
- Write research proposals
- Interview candidates / teach and train personnel

Jan 2002 – Jan 2017

# Coordinator

BC Cancer Agency - Genome Sciences Centre, Vancouver BC

- Lead bioinformatics software R&D
- Published research in reputed journals / international conferences
- Developed marketing (web portals / news release)
- Supervised a team of biologists and programmers
- Interviewed job candidates, taught and trained employees

Jan 2000 – Dec 2001

#### Officer

National Research Council - Biotechnology Research Institute, Montreal QC

- Co-engineered a system for regulating gene expression in cells
- Designed, fabricated and tested components of the DNA "gene switch"
- Work led to a patent, technology sold to company
- Integrated technology in viral and cell systems

# **EDUCATION**

Sep 2005 – Jun 2006	Management Courses Provincial Health Services Authority, Vancouver, Canada
Sep 2000 –	Cert. Computer Science
Dec 2001	Concordia University, Montréal, Canada
Jun 1997 –	MSc Biochemistry & Molecular Biology
Aug 1999	University of British Columbia, Vancouver, Canada
Sep 1994 –	<b>BSc Biochemistry</b> Dean's Honours List
May 1997	Université de Montréal, Montréal, Canada

# ADDITIONAL INFORMATION

2015, 16	Recipient of the John Jambor Knowledge Fund travel award
2011	Interviewed by NTN24 channel for Fusobacterium discovery colon cancer
2009	Interviewed by Genome Technology to discuss next-generation sequencing
2007	Interviewed by GenomeWeb for the development of SSAKE
1998	UBC Graduate Fellowship awarded for MSc
1997	Fonds de la Recherche en Santé Québec (FRSQ) awarded for BSc
1996	Bursary from FRSQ for BSc honour's research project
1995	Worked at NASA to coordinate the crystallization of proteins under
	microgravity [ CMIX-4 payload, space shuttle Endeavour ]

# PRESENTATIONS (selected from 15)

2017	Research in Computational Molecular Biology, Hong Kong – talk
2015, 16	Intelligent Systems for Molecular Biology, Dublin UK / Orlando USA - talks
2008, 12, 15	Pacific Symposium on Biocomputing, Kona, Hawaii USA – posters
2010	Sequencing, Finishing and Analysis in the Future, Santa Fe USA – talk
2007	Synthetic Biology 3.0 conference, Zürich, Switzerland – talk

# **PUBLICATIONS** (selected from 50)

\*co-first authors

Yeo S\*, Coombe L\*, Chu J, **Warren RL\***, Birol I. (2017) ARCS: Assembly Roundup by Chromium Scaffolding. TBD

Coombe L\*, **Warren RL**\*, et al. (2016) Assembly of the complete Sitka spruce chloroplast genome using 10X Genomics' GemCode sequencing data. *PLoS ONE*. 11(9): e0163059

**Warren RL**, *et al.* (2015) LINKS: Scalable, alignment-free scaffolding of draft genomes with long reads. *GigaScience* 4:35

Warren RL, et al. (2012) Derivation of HLA types from shotgun sequence datasets. Genome Med. 4:95 Castellarin M\*, Warren RL\*, et al. (2012) Fusobacterium nucleatum infection is prevalent in human colorectal carcinoma. Genome Research. 22:299-306

Warren RL, et al. (2007) Assembling millions of short DNA sequences using SSAKE. Bioinformatics. 23:500

E Allen-Vercoe, R Holt, R Moore, **R Warren.** Detection of fusobacterium in a gastrointestinal sample to diagnose gastrointestinal cancer. US Patent App. 13/877,421 / WO Patent 2,012,045,150

# **REFERENCES**

Available upon request